There was a person who ordained as a monk in Buddhism and went to ask Lord Buddha about it.
มี ร่าง หนึ่ง พี่ สุ มา บวช ใน พระศาสนา แล้ว เข้าไป ทูลถาม พระพุทธเจ้า ว่า.
What are the duties of a monk after ordination? Lord Buddha said that a monk has two duties.
พระ เมื่อ บวช มา แล้ว มี หน้าที่ อะไร บ้าง ท่าน บอ กว่า หน้าที่ พระ มี สอง อย่าง.
First, study the Dhamma and teach meditation.
หนึ่ง เรียน คันถธุระ สอน เรียน วิปัสสนาธุระ.
He asked what the Dhamma was and the various elements of love. It means studying scriptures, ordination, and learning
ท่าน ถาม ต่อว่า คันถธุระ คือ หลาย ขั้น ธาตุ รัก ก็ คือ เรียนหนังสือ คือ บวช และ ต้อง
What to study? Study the Tripitaka.
เรียน เรียน อะไร เรียน พระไตรปิฎก.
The second duty is meditation.
อัน ที่สอง วิปัสสนาธุระ.
It means applying the knowledge learned from the Tripitaka.
ก็ คือ การ เอา ความรู้ ที่ เรียน จาก พระไตรปิฎก นั่นแหละ.
Examine the body and its impermanence.
มา พิจารณา โดย พิจารณา ร่างกาย ความเสื่อม.
The untruthfulness of the body.
ความ ไม่ เที่ยงแท้ ของ ร่างกาย.
So that the mind doesn't cling to the body.
เผื่อ มา ให้ จิต นั้น มัน ยึดติด กับ ร่างกาย เหล่านั้น.
These are the two duties of a monk.
นี่ คือ หน้าที่ สอง อย่าง ของ พระ.
Now, there are two types of meditation study: the meditation season has two
เดี๋ยวนี้ การเรียน วิปัสสนา เนี่ย ก็ มี อยู่ สอง แบบ ฤดู การเรียน อา วิปัสสนาธุระ มี สอง
One is called Samatha Kammatthana.
แบบ หนึ่ง ก็ เรียก ว่า สมถะ กรรมฐาน.
The second is called Vipassana Kammatthana.
สอง เรียก ว่า วิปัสสนา กรรมฐาน.
Samatha Kammatthana means studying to bring about mental peace.
สมถะ กรรมฐาน คือ เรียน เพื่อที่จะ ให้ เกิด ความสงบ ของ จิต.
That is, the human mind is confused, restless, and overthinking. We think about various things every day, and we think
คือ จิต มนุษย์ แนบ มัน สับสน มัน วุ่นวาย มัน คิดมาก หม้าย แต่ละ เรื่อง แต่ละวัน เรา คิด
Too much. From the moment we wake up until we fall asleep.
เยอะแยะ ไป หมด. ตั้งแต่ ตื่นนอน จน หลับ นั่นแหละ.
Sometimes even dreaming continues, with that punch.
บางที หลับ และ ยัง ฝัน ต่อ อีก ด้วย ประ หมัด นั้น.
The content of the method, how not to make the mind so that it can be calm.
เนื้อหา วิธี อย่า ทำใจ อย่างไร ให้ มัน สงบ ได้.
He taught to develop concentration.
ท่าน ไกรสร ให้ เจริญ สมาธิ.
When the mind becomes peaceful, continue to cultivate it. Use that peacefulness as a foundation, as a mental state.
เมื่อ จิต เกิด ความสงบ แล้ว ให้ เจริญ ต่อ ด้วย เอา ความสงบ นั้น มา เป็น อารมณ์ เป็น
Then contemplate and see deeper than that.
กรรมฐาน แล้วก็ ให้ พิจารณา ให้ เห็น ลึก ไป กว่า นั้น.
Look and see that our body is not constant, it is suffering, and it cannot find a state of self.
มอง ให้ เห็น ว่า ร่างกาย เรา เนี่ย มัน ไม่เที่ยง มัน เป็นทุกข์ แล้วก็ มัน หา สภาพ
Once you understand this, it is said that this is the attainment of Dharma.
เมื่อ เข้าใจ ตรงนี้ แล้ว ท่าน บอก กว่า นั่นแหละ คือ การ บรรลุ ธรรม.
But today, we will talk about meditation, cultivating Dharma, and sometimes,
แต่ นี้ วันนี้ เรา จะ พูด เรื่อง สมาธิ เนี่ย เรื่อง การ เจริญ ธรรมะ เรื่อง การ บาง ครั้ง
In the Buddha's time, he used the term "cultivating the Dharma".
ใน สมัย พุทธกาล ท่าน ใช้ คำ ว่า เจริญสมณธรรม.
Nowadays, we use the term "cultivating meditation".
สมัยนี้ เรา ใช้ คำ ว่า เจริญ สมาธิ.
Why do we need to cultivate meditation?
ถาม ว่า ทำไม เรา ต้อง เจริญ สมาธิ.
The reason we need to cultivate meditation is that our mind is definitely chaotic, agitated, and restless.
เหตุ ที่ เรา จ้อง เจริญ สมาธิ ก็เพราะว่า จิต เรา แน่ ๆ มัน มัน มัน สับสน มัน กวัดแกว่ง มัน
The speaker compared our mind to a monkey, which is very hyperactive. When a monkey is released in a house, it destroys the house!
วุ่นวาย. ท่าน เปรียบ จิต ของ เรา นั้น เหมือน ลิง ตัว หนึ่ง ที่ มัน ซน ซน เน ลิง ใน อยู่
In the end, it wreaks havoc in the garden, tearing flowers and leaves apart. That is the story of the monkey.
ปลาย ใน สวน เมื่อ กระ เก็บ ดอกไม้ ใบไม้ ทิ้ง เรี่ยราด ไป หมด ละ นั่น เป็นเรื่อง ของ ลิง
The speaker then compares our restless mind to a monkey.
ท่าน จึง เปรียบ จิต รา วนา มัน เหมือน ลิง.
But the question is, why do we need to practice meditation? We need to train the monkey to obey.
แต่ ได้ ถาม ว่า ทำไม ทำไม ต้อง ฝึก สมาธิ ก็ ต้องการ ฝึก ลิงก์ ให้ มัน เชื่อ ไง.
Why do we need to practice meditation? We need to practice meditation because our mind needs to be trained to be still. This is the
ทำไม ต้อง ฝึก สมาธิ ต้อง ฝึก สมาธิ จิต เรา ต้องการ ฝึก กิจธุระ ให้ มัน นิ่ง ไง นี่ คือ
reason why we need to practice and be still, and how it is beneficial. When we are still, we can see
เหตุผล ว่า ทำไม เรา ต้อง ฝึก และ นิ่ง และ มันดี อย่างไร นิ่ง และ เรา จะ ได้ เห็น
the truth of all things within ourselves. We will see the impermanence of everything.
ความจริง ของ สรรพสิ่ง ใน ตัวตน ของ เรา เรา จะ เห็น อนิจจัง ทุก ขัง อนัตตา.
The term "seeing the impermanence of everything" does not mean seeing because someone else told us, but seeing because we
คำ ว่า เห็น อนิจจัง ทุก ขัง อนัตตา ไม่ เห็น เพราะ มี พระ ญาณ บอก ไม่ ใช่ เห็น เพราะว่า คน
have been taught to see.
นั้น มา สอน แต่ เห็น.
With one's own mind, because peace arises, wisdom arises due to vipassana (insight meditation). That's it.
ด้วย จิต ของ ตนเอง เพราะ ความสงบ เกิดขึ้น ปัญญา ด้วยว่า วิปัสสนา ปัญญา เกิดขึ้น นั่น
Then, one will truly see the peace and chaos and understand that everything is impermanent.
ล่ะ มัน จะ เห็น เห็นจริง เห็น ความสงบ เห็น ความวุ่นวาย แล้ว เข้าใจ ว่า ทุกอย่าง มัน เป็น
Everything is anicca (impermanent), dukkha (suffering), and anatta (non-self). The term anicca means not lasting, the term dukkha means unable to endure.
อนิจจัง ทุก ขัง อนัตตา คำ ว่า อนิจจัง คือ ไม่ เที่ยงแท้ คำ ว่า ทุกข์ ขัง คือ มัน ทน
In the same condition, the term anatta means it cannot find its true self, even this table.
อยู่ ใน สภาพเดิม ไม่ ได้ คำ ว่า อนัตตา มัน หา ตัวตน ที่ แท้จริง ของ มัน ไม่ ได้ แม้แต่
One day, it will have to break down and become something else. If it burns, it turns into ashes.
โต๊ะ ตัว นี้ วันหนึ่ง มัน ก็ ต้อง สลาย กลาย เป็น อย่าง อื่น ถ้า ถูก ไฟไหม้ ก็ กลายเป็น
Ultimately, it returns to the natural law. That's the anatta of all phenomena.
ขี้เถ้า. ท้ายที่สุด มัน ก็ คืน สูตร ธรรมชาติ นั่น คือ อนัตตา ของ สรรพสิ่ง ทั้งหลาย ภาย
There is a question of why we should develop concentration, because our minds are confused and chaotic.
นั้น เหมือน มี มี คำถาม ว่า ทำไม ต้อง เจริญ สมาธิ เพราะ จิต เรา มัน สับสน มัน วุ่นวาย.
The mind struggles, it swings and wavers. The mind is like a restless palace.
มัน ดิ้นรน มัน กวัดแกว่ง พันธะ นาง จิต ดัง บัลลังก์ จิตตัง จิต มัน ดิ้นรน จิต มั่น
It swings and wavers, and the mind's thread is not peaceful. Because the mind is not peaceful, we have suffering.
กวัดแกว่ง จิต มัน ซัด สาย มัน ไม่ สงบ เพราะ จิต ไม่ สงบ เรา จึง มี ทุกข์ เพราะ เรา อยาก
To extinguish suffering, we must develop the foundation of actions or train the mind, or we must develop concentration and meditation.
จะ ดับทุกข์ เรา จึง ต้อง เจริญ กรรมฐาน หรือ เรา จึง ต้อง ฝึก จิต หรือ เรา ต้อง เจริญ
Wishful thinking.
สมาธิ ภาวนา.